Counting sort algorithm.
Is sorting algorithm that sorts the elements of an array by counting the number of occurrences of each
unique element in the array, that count is stored in an auxiliary array and that sort thing is done
by mapping the count as an index of the axillary array.
I know you don't understand anything about we are going to clarify all of these written content and
we by solving the exercises and implementing their algorithm in Java and C.
So counting sort is used when there are smaller integer with multiple counts and when there is linear
complexity is needed, the first step is find out the maximum element.
Let it be the maximum four from that given array.
We have a we find max.
And then in shallows, an array of lengths, maximum +1.
So we have maximum array element is eight and we initialize an array of max f lengths max +1 with all
the elements zeros in the previous example.
Here we have seven elements.
OK, we have.
This array that contains seven elements, the maximum element between them is eight.
The second step is to create an array that contains eight elements because it is maximum plus one,
a seven plus one.
It is eight with all elements at zero.
This area is used for starting the count of the elements in there.
We start counting the elements of currencies in the Saturday store, the count of each element at their
respective index in the count array.
For example, if the count of Element three is due, then two is stored in the third position of the
count.
This is the count array that are that it is enclosed with zeros, and we took an example that if the
Element three is due, the count of the Element three is two.
So we go here that we have, if we look at City, we have one and two.
So there is two elements, there is two cities here, and we stored it at index third.
If we took an example, Element five is not present in the air raid, then zero is stored in the fifth
position.
So here we are playing with with the indices that indicates that no, so far the Fifth Element, the
fifth index will be representing the fifth.
The number five in this array.
So this are three we have two occurrences of three.
We go to the third index and we put two.
We have two two occurrences of do so.
If we go here, we have two currencies of two.
If we go to four, we have one.
So we go to the fourth element and we store one.
And one also is here and zeros for the six and seven and zero because we don't have any zero, any five
and six, and it's only one element at eight.
So here we have one element.
Eight.
We store it at index eight one.
This is, they're counting it.
So after that, we start a store cumulative.
Some of the elements of that count array.
It helps in placing the elements into the correct index of the stored at a zero zero one one two and
three three five four six five six and six zero six seven six and eight seven.
OK.
This is the store, the cumulative.
Some of the elements of that count are they we we some here like?
For this is Tara, and this is the count.
So.
For at index four four minus six is equal for a six minus one, is equal to five and store it at five.
So find the index of each element of the original array in the count of three.
This will gives that cumulative count a place the elements at element at the index calculated as shown
in the figure below.
So this theory and this is the cumulative count this cumulative count will indicates four four which
search for Fourth Element Fourth Element we put six minus one is equal to five.
So we go and store it in the output array.
Function five.
The Fifth Element 5th Index we store number four.
OK.
This is the algorithm after placing each element at its correct position, decrease its count by one.
So we decrease it by one here.
OK, go for that.
Three have increased and decreased by the counting sort algorithm.
We start by making a function.
Counting sort took an array that we are going to sort, and the size of it we find the maximum largest
element in the array, initialize the count array with all zeros, and then we make a loop from zero
to two size.
We find the total count of each unique element and store that count at that JS index in that count array.
Then we make a for loop less at the from y minus one to index from one to maximum and find that cumulative
sum and store it in the count array itself.
We update it with that cumulative sum and then we fought for that.
J is for less than and sized down to one looping through all the elements, restarted the elements to
array and decrease the count to each element stored by one.
Let's see that counting sorting a assorted algorithm complexity the best case it's and plus K and the
worst case is and plus K and the average case is and a plus game goes.
It's depending on that counting and making aspect in New A and store them with time, complexity and
plus k.
The space complexity is oh two max because.
And the first step, we select the maximum element after that, we make an array with max +1, so it
will depend on the maximum and the stability.
It is stable and the next video we are going to implement there counting sort.